<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Inkspire - Featured Post</title>
    <subtitle>A elegant and modern theme for Zola</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://josegarcia.dev/categories/featured-post/atom.xml" />
    <link
        rel="alternate"
        type="text/html"
        href="https://josegarcia.dev"
    />
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated
    >2025-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://josegarcia.dev/categories/featured-post/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Why Zola Might Be Your Next Static Site Generator</title>
        <published>2025-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated
        >2025-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Jose Garcia
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link
            rel="alternate"
            type="text/html"
            href="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/why-zola-might-be-your-next-ssg/"
        />
        <id>https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/why-zola-might-be-your-next-ssg/</id>
        
        <content
            type="html"
            xml:base="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/why-zola-might-be-your-next-ssg/"
        >&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re in the market for a static site generator, you&#x27;ve probably encountered the usual suspects: Hugo, Jekyll, Gatsby, Astro. But there&#x27;s a compelling alternative that deserves your attention: Zola.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-zola-different&quot;&gt;What Makes Zola Different&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola is a static site generator built in Rust, which immediately gives it two advantages: blazing speed and zero dependencies. Unlike Jekyll (which requires Ruby) or Hugo (which needs Go), Zola is distributed as a single binary. Download it, and you&#x27;re ready to build.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simplicity extends to the entire development experience. While other generators require you to manage plugin ecosystems and dependency chains, Zola ships with everything built-in: Sass compilation, syntax highlighting, image processing, and a powerful templating engine called Tera.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;built-for-developers-who-value-speed&quot;&gt;Built for Developers Who Value Speed&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance is noticeable. Zola rebuilds sites almost instantaneously, making the local development experience smooth and interruption-free. The live reload is fast enough that you can see changes as you type.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But speed isn&#x27;t just about build times. Zola&#x27;s approach to content organization is straightforward: sections, pages, and taxonomies. There&#x27;s no complex abstraction layer to learn. If you understand how your content should be structured, you can map it directly to Zola&#x27;s concepts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-zola-shines&quot;&gt;Where Zola Shines&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multilingual support is first-class in Zola, not an afterthought. You can create content in multiple languages without wrestling with plugins or custom configurations. The documentation is clear, and the patterns are consistent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The templating system, Tera, strikes a good balance between power and simplicity. It&#x27;s Jinja2-inspired, so if you&#x27;ve worked with Python or Ansible, you&#x27;ll feel at home. Macros, filters, and template inheritance work as you&#x27;d expect.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-trade-offs&quot;&gt;The Trade-offs&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s ecosystem is smaller than Hugo&#x27;s or Gatsby&#x27;s. You won&#x27;t find thousands of themes or plugins. This is both a constraint and a feature—it pushes you to build exactly what you need rather than cobbling together plugins that might conflict.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation is generally solid, though some advanced use cases require digging into GitHub issues or the community forum. The project is actively maintained, but it&#x27;s a smaller team compared to other generators.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-zola-right-for-you&quot;&gt;Is Zola Right for You?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you value simplicity, speed, and a single-binary distribution over a massive ecosystem, Zola is worth trying. It&#x27;s particularly well-suited for blogs, documentation sites, and portfolios where you want full control without complexity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The learning curve is gentle, the builds are fast, and you&#x27;ll spend more time writing content than configuring your build pipeline. Sometimes that&#x27;s exactly what you need.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Zola vs Astro: Traditional SSG Meets Modern JavaScript</title>
        <published>2025-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated
        >2025-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Jose Garcia
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link
            rel="alternate"
            type="text/html"
            href="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-astro-traditional-ssg-meets-modern-javascript/"
        />
        <id>https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-astro-traditional-ssg-meets-modern-javascript/</id>
        
        <content
            type="html"
            xml:base="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-astro-traditional-ssg-meets-modern-javascript/"
        >&lt;p&gt;At first glance, comparing Zola and Astro might seem odd. One is a traditional static site generator built in Rust. The other is a modern JavaScript framework with an islands architecture. But both excel at building fast static sites, and both claim to make the process simpler. The question is: which kind of simplicity do you need?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;philosophy-everything-included-vs-bring-your-own&quot;&gt;Philosophy: Everything Included vs Bring Your Own&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola ships as a single binary with everything built-in. Download one file, and you have templating, Sass compilation, syntax highlighting, image processing, and live reload. No npm, no node_modules, no build configuration.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro is a JavaScript framework that embraces the npm ecosystem. You install it via npm, configure it through JavaScript, and extend it with integrations. Want to use React components? Install the React integration. Need Tailwind? Add it. The philosophy is composition over inclusion.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#x27;t a value judgment—it&#x27;s a fundamental difference in approach. Zola says &quot;here&#x27;s everything you need.&quot; Astro says &quot;here&#x27;s a foundation, add what you want.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;installation-and-setup&quot;&gt;Installation and Setup&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting started with Zola:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Download binary
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Add to PATH
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;zola&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; init my-site
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;zola&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; serve
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting started with Astro:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;npm&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; create astro@latest
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Answer interactive prompts
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;npm&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; run dev
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s approach means no node_modules folder, no package.json, no dependency updates. Your project is just your content and templates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro&#x27;s approach means you&#x27;re in the JavaScript ecosystem with all its benefits and complexities. You get access to npm packages, but you also manage dependencies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;component-model-templates-vs-javascript-components&quot;&gt;Component Model: Templates vs JavaScript Components&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola uses Tera templates. You write HTML with template syntax for loops, conditionals, and macros. It&#x27;s server-side templating—what you write is what gets rendered to HTML.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro lets you write components in Astro syntax (which looks like JSX) and can integrate React, Vue, Svelte, or Solid components. You can mix and match frameworks in the same project. This is powerful if you want to reuse existing components or prefer a component-driven architecture.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the trade-off: Zola&#x27;s templates are simpler but less powerful for interactive components. Astro&#x27;s components are more complex but give you the full JavaScript ecosystem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-management&quot;&gt;Content Management&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both use Markdown for content, but they handle it differently.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola has a structured content model with sections and pages. Front matter is strict but predictable. You organize content by directories, and Zola automatically generates routes. It&#x27;s opinionated about structure, which reduces decisions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro is more flexible. You can put Markdown files anywhere, use content collections for structured data, or pull content from CMSs or APIs at build time. This flexibility is useful for complex sites but requires more decision-making.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance-both-fast-different-reasons&quot;&gt;Performance: Both Fast, Different Reasons&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola is fast because it&#x27;s Rust. Build times are measured in milliseconds. It rebuilds incrementally during development, and changes appear nearly instantly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro is fast because it ships zero JavaScript by default. Your site is pure HTML and CSS unless you opt into client-side interactivity. When you do add JavaScript, Astro&#x27;s islands architecture only hydrates the components that need it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, both produce fast sites. Zola achieves this through traditional static generation. Astro achieves it through clever JavaScript optimization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;interactivity-and-javascript&quot;&gt;Interactivity and JavaScript&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the paths diverge significantly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola doesn&#x27;t have a story for complex client-side interactivity. You can add vanilla JavaScript, but if you need a React component or Vue widget, you&#x27;re integrating it manually. Zola excels at static, content-focused sites.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro was built for partial hydration. You can have an entirely static blog post with one interactive widget that loads React only for that component. This is Astro&#x27;s killer feature—progressive enhancement through islands architecture.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your site is mostly static with occasional interactivity, Astro gives you a clear path forward. If your site is entirely static, Zola&#x27;s simplicity might be preferable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;styling-and-assets&quot;&gt;Styling and Assets&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola has built-in Sass compilation. Write &lt;code&gt;.scss&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; files, and Zola handles them. For other assets, you put them in the static folder, and they&#x27;re copied as-is.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro integrates with modern tooling. You can use Tailwind, CSS-in-JS, CSS Modules, or whatever the JavaScript ecosystem offers. Asset optimization happens through Vite, Astro&#x27;s build tool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s approach is simpler but more limited. Astro&#x27;s approach gives you more options but requires configuration.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ecosystem-and-integrations&quot;&gt;Ecosystem and Integrations&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s ecosystem is minimal. There are some themes and a small community. You&#x27;re mostly building from scratch or adapting existing HTML&#x2F;CSS templates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro&#x27;s ecosystem is growing rapidly. There are integrations for CMSs, image optimization, analytics, and more. You can use any npm package. The community is active, and new integrations appear regularly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to integrate with modern web development tools—TypeScript, Tailwind, MDX, image optimization, analytics—Astro makes this straightforward. With Zola, you&#x27;re on your own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;multilingual-sites&quot;&gt;Multilingual Sites&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola has first-class multilingual support. Create content in multiple languages, and Zola handles routing and structure automatically. It&#x27;s straightforward and requires minimal configuration.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro supports multilingual sites through routing configuration and content collections. It&#x27;s more manual but also more flexible. You control exactly how languages are handled.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-curve&quot;&gt;Learning Curve&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s learning curve is gentle if you know HTML and are comfortable with template syntax. There&#x27;s one templating language to learn (Tera), and the mental model is simple: templates render content to HTML.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro&#x27;s learning curve depends on your JavaScript experience. If you&#x27;re comfortable with modern JavaScript, JSX, and component thinking, Astro feels natural. If you&#x27;re new to this ecosystem, there&#x27;s more to learn: component syntax, props, islands, integrations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;developer-experience&quot;&gt;Developer Experience&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s DX is about simplicity. Fast builds, simple mental model, no toolchain configuration. You focus on content and templates. The live reload is nearly instant.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astro&#x27;s DX is about power and flexibility. You get TypeScript support, component frameworks, modern tooling, and extensive integrations. The development server is fast, and error messages are helpful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-choose-astro&quot;&gt;When to Choose Astro&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick Astro if you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need to mix static content with interactive components&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want to use React, Vue, or Svelte components&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need integration with modern JavaScript tooling&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan to pull content from APIs or CMSs&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want TypeScript support out of the box&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need to progressively enhance static pages with interactivity&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are comfortable with npm and JavaScript tooling&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-choose-zola&quot;&gt;When to Choose Zola&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick Zola if you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want zero dependency installation and maintenance&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are building a content-focused site (blog, docs, portfolio)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer simplicity over flexibility&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&#x27;t need complex client-side interactivity&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want built-in Sass without configuration&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value fast builds with minimal tooling&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer a single binary over a JavaScript toolchain&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-decision-point&quot;&gt;The Real Decision Point&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice between Zola and Astro isn&#x27;t about which is better—it&#x27;s about which model fits your project and preferences.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose based on your site&#x27;s needs:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pure static content with minimal interactivity? Zola&#x27;s simplicity shines.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix of static content and interactive components? Astro&#x27;s islands architecture is perfect.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want to avoid JavaScript tooling entirely? Zola gives you that.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need the JavaScript ecosystem and its packages? Astro provides access.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both will give you fast, performant sites. Zola does it with traditional static generation and zero dependencies. Astro does it with modern JavaScript tooling and optional interactivity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither is wrong. Pick the one that matches how you want to work, not just what you want to build.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Zola vs Hugo: Choosing Between Two Speed Demons</title>
        <published>2025-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated
        >2025-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Jose Garcia
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link
            rel="alternate"
            type="text/html"
            href="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-hugo-choosing-between-two-speed-demons/"
        />
        <id>https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-hugo-choosing-between-two-speed-demons/</id>
        
        <content
            type="html"
            xml:base="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-hugo-choosing-between-two-speed-demons/"
        >&lt;p&gt;When you&#x27;re picking a static site generator and performance matters, the conversation usually narrows down to two contenders: Hugo and Zola. Both are exceptionally fast, both compile to single binaries, and both can handle large sites without breaking a sweat. So how do you choose?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-single-binary-promise&quot;&gt;The Single Binary Promise&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s start with what they share: neither Hugo nor Zola requires you to install a language runtime. No npm, no Ruby gems, no Python virtual environments. You download a binary, add it to your path, and you&#x27;re building sites. This is a massive advantage over Jekyll or Gatsby.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo is written in Go. Zola is written in Rust. From a user perspective, this distinction rarely matters, except that Rust&#x27;s reputation for safety means Zola crashes are exceptionally rare—though to be fair, Hugo is rock-solid too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-speed-both-winners&quot;&gt;Build Speed: Both Winners&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth? Both are absurdly fast. Hugo claims to build sites in milliseconds. Zola does the same. For most projects under a few thousand pages, the difference is imperceptible. You&#x27;ll spend more time waiting for your browser to refresh than for either tool to rebuild.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where they diverge is in what comes next. Hugo&#x27;s speed has led to massive sites—think 50,000+ pages. Zola is fast enough for most use cases, but it hasn&#x27;t been battle-tested at that scale the same way Hugo has.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ecosystem-size-vs-simplicity&quot;&gt;Ecosystem: Size vs Simplicity&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo wins on ecosystem size, and it&#x27;s not close. There are hundreds of themes, extensive documentation, and a large community. If you&#x27;re building a documentation site, Hugo&#x27;s ecosystem has mature solutions ready to use.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s ecosystem is deliberately smaller. There are fewer themes, fewer plugins, and a smaller community. This sounds like a disadvantage until you realize it&#x27;s also freeing. You&#x27;re not sifting through outdated themes or debugging plugin conflicts. You build what you need.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is: do you want a marketplace or a workshop?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;templating-go-templates-vs-tera&quot;&gt;Templating: Go Templates vs Tera&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo uses Go&#x27;s template language. It&#x27;s powerful but has a learning curve, especially if you&#x27;re not familiar with Go. The syntax can feel verbose, and some operations that seem simple require looking up documentation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola uses Tera, which is based on Jinja2. If you&#x27;ve worked with Python, Django, or even Ansible, you&#x27;ll recognize the patterns immediately. Filters, macros, and template inheritance work intuitively. The syntax is cleaner and more consistent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is subjective, but for most developers, Tera is easier to pick up and more pleasant to work with.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-organization&quot;&gt;Content Organization&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo gives you tremendous flexibility in how you organize content. You can create custom content types, define complex taxonomies, and build intricate site structures. This power comes with complexity—Hugo&#x27;s content model has more concepts to learn.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola is more opinionated. You have sections, pages, and taxonomies. It&#x27;s simpler but less flexible. For blogs, documentation, and portfolios, this simplicity is usually an advantage. For complex sites with unusual structures, Hugo&#x27;s flexibility might be necessary.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;multilingual-support&quot;&gt;Multilingual Support&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both support multiple languages, but they approach it differently.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo has mature multilingual support with extensive configuration options. You can fine-tune how languages are handled, create language-specific menus, and manage translations with precision. It&#x27;s comprehensive but requires more setup.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s multilingual support is straightforward and built-in. You create content in different languages, and Zola handles the routing. It&#x27;s less configurable but requires almost no setup. For most multilingual sites, Zola&#x27;s approach is sufficient and much simpler.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;built-in-features-vs-extensibility&quot;&gt;Built-in Features vs Extensibility&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola ships with Sass compilation, syntax highlighting, and image processing out of the box. You don&#x27;t install plugins for these features—they&#x27;re just there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo requires external tools for some of these tasks or uses Hugo Pipes and Hugo Modules. It&#x27;s more modular, which gives you control but adds configuration complexity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;documentation-and-community&quot;&gt;Documentation and Community&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo&#x27;s documentation is extensive but can be overwhelming. There&#x27;s a lot to learn, and finding the right approach for your use case sometimes means reading through multiple sections.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s documentation is more concise and organized. It&#x27;s easier to find what you need quickly, though advanced use cases might require checking GitHub discussions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community size favors Hugo significantly. More Stack Overflow answers, more blog posts, more people who&#x27;ve solved the problem you&#x27;re facing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-choose-hugo&quot;&gt;When to Choose Hugo&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick Hugo if you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need proven scalability for massive sites (10,000+ pages)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want a rich ecosystem of themes and tools&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Require complex content modeling and relationships&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need extensive third-party integrations&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value the safety of following the most popular option&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-choose-zola&quot;&gt;When to Choose Zola&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick Zola if you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want the simplest possible setup and maintenance&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer building your own designs over adapting themes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like clean, intuitive templating syntax&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need built-in Sass and don&#x27;t want to configure build pipelines&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value a focused tool over an extensive ecosystem&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want straightforward multilingual support&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-difference&quot;&gt;The Real Difference&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo is a Swiss Army knife—it can do almost anything, but you need to learn which blade to use. Zola is a scalpel—it does fewer things, but it does them precisely and with minimal fuss.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither choice is wrong. The question is whether your project needs Hugo&#x27;s power and ecosystem, or whether Zola&#x27;s simplicity and elegance will let you ship faster and maintain easier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most blogs and documentation sites, Zola is enough. For complex, large-scale projects or when you want maximum flexibility, Hugo delivers. Choose based on your project&#x27;s needs, not the tool&#x27;s capabilities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Zola vs Pelican: Rust Simplicity Meets Python Flexibility</title>
        <published>2025-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated
        >2025-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Jose Garcia
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link
            rel="alternate"
            type="text/html"
            href="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-pelican-rust-simplicity-meets-python-flexibility/"
        />
        <id>https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-pelican-rust-simplicity-meets-python-flexibility/</id>
        
        <content
            type="html"
            xml:base="https://josegarcia.dev/articles/featured/zola-vs-pelican-rust-simplicity-meets-python-flexibility/"
        >&lt;p&gt;Pelican has been around since 2010, making it one of the oldest static site generators still actively maintained. It brought Python&#x27;s philosophy to static sites and has powered thousands of blogs. Zola is the new contender, built in Rust with a focus on speed and simplicity. Both are excellent tools, but they represent different eras and philosophies of web development.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;installation-virtual-environments-vs-single-binary&quot;&gt;Installation: Virtual Environments vs Single Binary&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican is a Python package. The typical installation looks like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;python -m&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; venv pelican-env
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; pelican-env&#x2F;bin&#x2F;activate
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;pip&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; install pelican&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;[&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;markdown&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;pelican-quickstart
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need Python installed, you&#x27;ll create a virtual environment (or you should), and you&#x27;ll manage dependencies through pip. This is standard for Python projects, but it&#x27;s still setup overhead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola is a single binary:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Download binary
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Add to PATH
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;zola&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; init my-site
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No Python, no virtual environment, no pip. One executable that contains everything. Update Zola by downloading a new binary. Your project has no external dependencies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This difference matters more than it might seem. With Pelican, you&#x27;re managing Python versions, virtual environments, and dependency conflicts. With Zola, you download one file and you&#x27;re done.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;templating-both-use-jinja-style-syntax&quot;&gt;Templating: Both Use Jinja-Style Syntax&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s where things get interesting: both Pelican and Zola use Jinja-inspired templating.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican uses actual Jinja2, Python&#x27;s most popular templating engine. If you&#x27;ve worked with Flask or Django, you already know how to template in Pelican. The ecosystem of Jinja2 filters and extensions is available.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola uses Tera, which is based on Jinja2 but implemented in Rust. The syntax is nearly identical. If you know Jinja2, you&#x27;ll understand Tera immediately. The differences are minor—a few filters work differently, and some advanced Jinja2 features aren&#x27;t available.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, this means the transition from Pelican to Zola (or vice versa) involves minimal template rewriting. Your mental model transfers directly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-speed-not-even-close&quot;&gt;Build Speed: Not Even Close&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where Rust shows its strength.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican&#x27;s build speed is acceptable for small to medium sites. For larger sites—think hundreds or thousands of posts—build times can stretch into minutes. Python&#x27;s interpreted nature and Pelican&#x27;s plugin architecture add overhead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola rebuilds sites in milliseconds. Even with thousands of pages, builds are measured in seconds, not minutes. During development, changes appear almost instantly. This difference becomes more pronounced as your site grows.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re migrating from Pelican and suddenly your builds complete in a fraction of the time, that&#x27;s not a mistake—that&#x27;s Rust.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;plugin-ecosystem-extensibility-vs-built-in-features&quot;&gt;Plugin Ecosystem: Extensibility vs Built-In Features&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican has a mature plugin ecosystem. Need RSS feeds? There&#x27;s a plugin. Want to integrate with external services? There&#x27;s probably a plugin. Need custom content processing? Write a Python plugin.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This extensibility is Pelican&#x27;s strength. If you&#x27;re comfortable with Python, you can extend Pelican to do almost anything. The plugin API is well-documented, and there are dozens of existing plugins to learn from.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola takes the opposite approach: no plugins. Everything you need is built-in. Sass compilation? Included. Syntax highlighting? Built-in. Image processing? It&#x27;s there. Taxonomies and pagination? Already implemented.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trade-off is clear: Pelican gives you extensibility through Python. Zola gives you completeness through built-in features. If what you need is already in Zola, you&#x27;re set. If you need custom behavior, Pelican&#x27;s plugin system is more flexible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-organization-and-metadata&quot;&gt;Content Organization and Metadata&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both use Markdown with front matter, but they organize content differently.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican&#x27;s content model is flexible but loose. You can organize files however you want, and Pelican will process them. Metadata is defined in the front matter, and you can add arbitrary custom fields. Categories and tags work as you&#x27;d expect from a blog platform.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola has a more structured content model with explicit sections and pages. The directory structure maps directly to URL structure. This is more opinionated but also more predictable. Taxonomies (categories, tags, etc.) are first-class concepts with dedicated configuration.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican&#x27;s flexibility is useful for complex or unusual site structures. Zola&#x27;s structure is clearer for straightforward blogs and documentation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;python-integration-pelican-s-unique-advantage&quot;&gt;Python Integration: Pelican&#x27;s Unique Advantage&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s something Zola can&#x27;t match: Pelican is Python, which means you can integrate Python code directly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to process data with pandas and generate posts from it? Easy in Pelican. Need to pull data from a Python API client? Write a plugin. Want to use Python&#x27;s scientific or data visualization libraries? They&#x27;re available.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This integration is powerful if you&#x27;re already in the Python ecosystem. If your workflow involves Python data processing, Jupyter notebooks, or scientific computing, Pelican lets you leverage those tools directly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola offers no equivalent. It&#x27;s a standalone binary with no scripting layer. What you get is what&#x27;s built-in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;theme-ecosystem&quot;&gt;Theme Ecosystem&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican has a substantial collection of themes accumulated over more than a decade. Some are dated, but there are mature, well-maintained options. The community has had years to refine designs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s theme ecosystem is smaller and newer. There are good themes available, but fewer options overall. You&#x27;re more likely to build your own or heavily customize what exists.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to grab a theme and start writing immediately, Pelican offers more choices. If you prefer building your own design, both work fine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;documentation-and-community&quot;&gt;Documentation and Community&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican&#x27;s documentation is comprehensive but shows its age. It&#x27;s complete, but finding specific information sometimes requires reading through multiple sections. The community is established—most questions have been answered somewhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola&#x27;s documentation is modern, well-organized, and easier to navigate. It&#x27;s written for today&#x27;s web development practices. The community is smaller but active and helpful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stack Overflow and blog posts favor Pelican due to its age, but Zola&#x27;s GitHub discussions are responsive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;multilingual-sites&quot;&gt;Multilingual Sites&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican supports multiple languages through configuration and the i18n subsites plugin. It works but requires setup and understanding of how Pelican handles translations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola has built-in multilingual support that requires minimal configuration. You create content in different languages, and Zola handles routing automatically. It&#x27;s simpler and more intuitive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;configuration&quot;&gt;Configuration&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican uses a Python configuration file (&lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). It&#x27;s flexible—you can run Python code in your config—but it&#x27;s also verbose. Configuration can become complex.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola uses TOML. It&#x27;s simpler and more declarative. What you see is what you get. There&#x27;s no code execution in config files, which makes them easier to understand but less flexible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;deployment-and-ci-cd&quot;&gt;Deployment and CI&#x2F;CD&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both deploy easily to static hosting, but there&#x27;s a practical difference.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican requires a Python environment in your CI&#x2F;CD pipeline. You install Python, set up a virtual environment, install dependencies, then build. This works fine but adds steps.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola is a single binary. Download it in CI, run it, done. Many CI systems have Zola pre-installed or available through simple package managers. The deployment script is shorter.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-choose-pelican&quot;&gt;When to Choose Pelican&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick Pelican if you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are already comfortable with Python and its ecosystem&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need to integrate Python libraries or data processing&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want extensive plugin extensibility&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer proven, mature technology&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need specific plugins that already exist&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work in a Python-heavy environment&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&#x27;t mind managing Python dependencies&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-choose-zola&quot;&gt;When to Choose Zola&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick Zola if you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want zero-dependency installation and deployment&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value fast build times, especially for larger sites&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer built-in features over plugins&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want straightforward multilingual support&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like modern, clean documentation&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need simple configuration&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want to avoid dependency management&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&#x27;t require Python-specific integrations&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;migration-path&quot;&gt;Migration Path&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re considering moving from Pelican to Zola, the good news is that templates will mostly transfer. Both use Jinja-style syntax, so your template knowledge carries over. Content is Markdown in both, though you&#x27;ll need to adjust front matter format.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main work is replicating any custom Pelican plugins you rely on. If you use standard features, migration is straightforward. If you have complex Python integrations, staying with Pelican might make more sense.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-question&quot;&gt;The Real Question&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing between Pelican and Zola isn&#x27;t about which is objectively better—it&#x27;s about which fits your context.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you embedded in the Python ecosystem? Do you need Python integrations? Do you value extensibility through code? Pelican makes sense.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you want simplicity? Do build times matter? Do you prefer minimal dependencies and modern tooling? Zola is compelling.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both will give you a fast static site. Pelican does it with Python&#x27;s flexibility and maturity. Zola does it with Rust&#x27;s speed and simplicity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick based on your workflow and priorities, not just the tool&#x27;s features. Sometimes the right choice is the one that gets out of your way and lets you focus on writing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
